[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
door / software software engineering
radio this is Robert bloomin I'm here at
Q con San Francisco 2016 with gilt na
Gil is the CTO and co-founder of Azul
his work with Java and virtual machine
technologies for over 20 years
pioneered Azul C for garbage collector
and other runtime technologies he is a
member of the JCP Executive Committee
and in 2006 was named one of the top 50
agenda centers in the tech industry by
silk ENCOM guilt
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks for the thing I also wish to
thank info queue the organizers of Q
Khan for kindly providing the room where
we're making this recording and that Q
con Gil is giving two talks this week
one Java SE state of the union and the
other understanding Hardware
transactional memory so Gil would you
like to tell the listeners anything more
about yourself I think introduction wise
that's pretty good but you know that's
sort of the dry bio stuff in general I
like to think of myself as an engineer a
software developer and I've been playing
with and building things for over 30
years ever since backs eleven seven 80s
and the first species were around all
the way to today we've gotten to build
software almost any layer operating
systems device drivers embedded systems
full-blown application servers
applications and now for the last decade
in some virtual machines
compilers garbage collectors cool things
that kind of do the hard work and are
also programmed in lots of languages so
I'd like to say that I've made a lot of
mistakes and have learned from a few of
them and you know a lot of what I end up
talking about in some cases is kind of
the lessons learned and things that I
see people repeatedly doing that I also
used to do and what we might be able to
do different about them I hope today we
can benefit from some of your lessons
learned about tail latency before we go
into tail latency could you define what
is latency latency as a term actually
has a fairly okay definition latency is
a reaction time it's a time from when
one of it happened until some other
event that results from it happens it's
not unique to software or computers for
example a chemical mixture has a latency
of reacting to putting something into it
but when we talk about latency in this
when we talk about applications or
networks we usually mean the time it
takes from some input until some output
happens from a request until a response
arise from a user clicked until they see
stuff on the screen or from a message
entering a system until something
happening at the other end of that same
system now this for me to the same point
when you translate or look at more
queueing theory terms rather than look
at latency as a term I usually like to
actually separate the parts and
observability you have the response time
which is the externally measured time
problem and you do something until
whatever impact happens and in queueing
theory that is broken into usually into
a service time and a wait time the
service time is how long it took for the
thing that you were doing to actually
happen and the wait time is how long you
were waiting until it started to happen
or after it's happened before you saw
the indication so you can think of a
time in a queue versus the time to
actually do the service I think the
important thing when people look at
those is that the only actual
more externally observable thing about
that is response time the internal times
are actually not externally observable
but they're dynamic actually affects
behavior so when you're modeling things
doing the difference we service time in
queue time and length matters I'm a user
and I turned to download web page or an
image what ice perceive is the sum of
all the service and wait times yes okay
and response time is the sum of later
time and service okay I found an article
when I was reading up about this called
how one-second cost amazon 1.6 billion
dollars in sales from this article it
says amazon calculated that a page load
slowdown of just one second could cost
at 1.6 billion in sales each year
google has calculated that by slowing
its search results by just four tenths
of a second they could lose 8 million
searches per day can you explain how can
what sounds like quite small degradation
in latency have such a huge economic
impact on a business so so I've look at
it in two parts one is the direct
question you asked how does that latency
behavior impact the business and why is
it so big but the other part is when I
when I look at summaries like these I
and firstly think of them as they're
fairly simplistic so for example if you
read the one-second slowdown of a web
page well does that mean one person saw
one second slower response time did
everybody see one second was it that the
average was one second longer which is
it and usually there's no good
description or answer same same for the
Google and Amazon description there's
usually happen because if you take what
the people who actually did the
technical work do and follow it all the
way to some written article somewhere
set it it gets censored and simplified
and dumbed down in the way the first
magazine writer didn't ya know those
details like I'm I'm almost one to bet
that this is not that the average if you
change the average length of a page by
that amount that is
I do believe that some change in length
to some of the pages has those kind of
effects but in our experience it is tail
latency a lot more than average latency
that has an impact on things like
revenue so to the actual question you're
asked of how come something so small has
a huge effect on revenue we can talk
about an example sector that we for some
reason and up working and a lot online
shopping for clothes now Amazon does a
lot of shopping for lots of things but
we found actually that for some reason
clothes shopping likes our product and
it took us a while to figure out that
that's a sector it's a result that these
days when people shop for clothes you
actually go through a shopping
experience and it tries to give you an
experience that's somewhat similar to
shopping for clothes normally so it's
not a dry you know let's read about this
TV or toaster pick the model I want and
then go look for a good price on it it's
it's literally a shopping and browsing
experience and it tends to be very
interactive in fact I think that the
only thing more interactive or more
interactivity and responsiveness is more
critical to it online is gaming gaming
is obviously very sensitive to glitches
and late shaker whatever it is but
online shopping is - and the
questionnaire is how would a tiny bit of
difference and responsiveness why would
one image out of a hundred being
slightly slower affect revenue the
answers to that are that if you make the
experience itself become disappointing
annoying laggy whatever it is you create
opportunities for people to just change
their minds changing your minds may just
be they got distracted by something or
it may be that they fought too hard and
decided not to buy that shirt that they
just bought end up in the shopping
basket maybe it's not a good idea and
they had a chance to think about it or
it could be just that this is too much
farther on I need to look through fifty
or hundred things and it takes too long
I'm not going to do it I'll go to the
competitors site where it runs smooth
those seem to have very real impact so
tiny tiny changes to the responsiveness
reactiveness and the design of pages
having a huge impact in the revenue that
can be extracted from the exact same
traffic that arrives at website use the
term tail latency which I want to focus
on if I have thousand requests and I
know the total wait time for each
request I could look at average standard
deviation 50th percentile how do you
define tail latency and and why do you
consider that the most important measure
so I actually don't really define it or
use it as a term as much when people
talk about that latency they usually
refer to the higher percentiles higher
could be 99 99.9 maybe five nines all
the way to the maximum it's not the main
part of where most things are so think
of it as the rare events that happen to
be longer than the rest an assumption
when we talk about tail it and see it's
always in a percentile term so think of
take all the response times you had sort
them and you're looking at the worst
ones so that 1% worst ones about one of
the thousand worst ones whatever that
happened that's the tail and the reason
I think people talk about tenancy is
because usually if you don't say telling
see they'll tend to talk about the
center or the median or the average of
the common case the reason the tails are
much more important in the common case
is because humans do not perceive a
common case humans did not forgive you
because your average is good humans do
not think of things as you know I ate a
bag of peanuts and on the average they
were tasty that one back peanut that's
what they remember my pain is what you
remember bad experience is what you
remember if you go to a restaurant and
you like the food there and you go there
every week and they give you bad food
you're probably not coming back or maybe
you'll come back if you're really loyal
and you get on one more chance but two
out of a thousand and you've lost your
business in in that's the actual
reaction that's the perception of
quality in response is not
as your comment it's how bad is it
that's good of that example of the
shopper who might want to look at 50
shirts before they pick one
do you have either some data or based on
your experience where do humans start to
perceive a site as being so is it 90
percentile 99 so first of all humans
respond perceived the worst case they
don't receive any percentiles if you ask
somebody how did the website respond
whatever the worst thing they saw that's
what they'll answer with yeah if you've
been using it for a whole week and it
only did a little circle thing one time
maybe don't forget about that one but if
you sit there and you're using the
website and you're looking at a hundred
shirts in three minutes it's the slowest
trip it's not the fastest shirt that's
for sure nobody cares how fast fastest
was nobody cares what the average is
nobody cares that most of the things you
get them good stuff they just care that
you slowed them down and that's true for
pretty much anything that's a human
experience
now beyond human experience there are
other places where latency matters not
just from a perception point of view and
that has to do with you know
requirements or reliability or risk you
know if you're in a trading system and
and you're making a bet because the
market conditions are a certain level
and you're gonna do some trade that
makes money assuming the market
conditions don't change then if the
market conditions change there's a risk
that you lose a lot of money and longer
the latency it's a longer the risk is
it's enough for there to be one in a
million chance or something that happens
it cost you a million times more to
completely offset all your profits so
it's a risk reward risk cost computation
of it and so when we can find it in
other systems where if you look at
common modern microservice architectures
for example a normal way to design
microservices so that failures do not
cascade and and bring down your entire
infrastructure to prevent services from
overwhelming other services to wrap up
what you were saying
maybe in retail once per hour once per
day is too much whatever that translates
into but once a week would be acceptable
whereas in the trading system you
describe even one out of a million
latency spikes might be out of
requirements for that system those are
not I wouldn't use those as specific for
the sector it could be one over a
thousand one of it's that rare events
matter yes to question about the human
perception parts I think that humans
perceive hi tens of milliseconds too low
hundreds of milliseconds there's
definitely the ability to differentiate
those these days and this has changed in
the trends over the years
snappy website responsiveness is in the
order of a hundred milliseconds if you
want to try and think of it for yourself
think of typing into an autocomplete
field for a search and what kind of lag
would you accept before the next
autocomplete shows up before you think
this is like sure that is in the level
of 100 200 milliseconds at most today
where if you go back five 10 years ago
people would have easily accepted a
second as acceptable because they
weren't out of completely we're talking
about a late see of hitting a single end
point modern web pages you might be
running JavaScript that's hitting a
hundred endpoints to show you the page
all those endpoints are gonna have
different latency characteristics what
does the user perceive on a complex
modern web page as responsive so the
answer is probably complicated it has to
do as much with the design of the page
as anything else but if we put aside the
design of the page suppose the actual
information that you are presented with
is what we're talking about not the
axillary unnecessary information we
might want to show you but it's okay if
you don't see right so in a shopping
scenario I just popped up stuff and I'm
gonna look at 30 shirts when do I see
the 30 shirts
Pachi and some of them are not here but
when do I got the set to consider and
browse to and remember since this is
supposed to feel like shopping until
they all show up you don't bother to
look at the rest so it's all it's the
center that arrangement we're trying to
showing if those 30 things involve say
50 or 100 separate HTTP requests whether
they're for this to the same server or
different servers doesn't matter the
human will say my click is complete when
the data is in front of them when it
stopped moving when they can actually
start contemplating and reading it
there's a lot of interesting tricks that
are done in web design to try and get
you to that point before everything has
been delivered and that's the design of
the page you know maybe you could start
reading the article before the ad is
showed up and it won't reformat you mate
but if you start reading in the shape of
the page changes because an ad showed up
you consider that annoying in fact it
would rather not even start reading
somebody's going to change the shape of
the page after you start so that's so I
actually like to highlight the
difference between the perceived
response time of the consumer which was
a human in this case or maybe in a
service that made a request and the set
of individual operations that came into
producing that so if you click on a web
page and 97 requests go out 97 responses
come back in and you see the information
then one of my response times involves
97 other response times and my worst
response time or my response time will
be the worst of 97 okay so I'm going to
give an example that's bit dumb down
bits because I can do the math in my
head right now but if I'm gonna view a
hundred shirts and each one is gonna
make 10 API calls I'm making a thousand
API calls and if I know one out of a
thousand of them it's gonna take a
second the page is gonna take a second
yeah that's a good roughly to think
about it if you actually look at it from
a viability perspective it doesn't mean
that every picture will take a second
that means that there's
a one in a thousand ^ a thousand yes yes
dependent probability so there are some
pages that will not see this and there's
some pages and one of this but without
doing any correlative things you know if
one and a thousand things go bad and you
do a thousand things then most of the
pages you do with a vast majority of the
pages you're looking at will have the
bad thing in that's a good explanation
or an example of how something that
would be considered at a latency to one
thing that HTTP response time is by no
means the ten latency to the human the
median latency the human will see will
be the 99.9% out of the HTTP request
because there's a thousand requests on
each page so a tail to one thing maybe a
common case so I can't do this math in
my head right now but if you think users
gonna visit your site every day for a
week and you're willing to let them have
one bad page view a week and each time
they visit your site they view ten pages
each page is a thousand API calls then
the level you need to meet your
requirement is quite high yeah I can't
leave your own cache location and it's
probably one you can't afford the good
news is people are forgiving enough the
once a week a slow page is not going to
make you think you're slow and they're
probably gonna blame Comcast instead of
you for it but if but if you
systemically are slower than another
site they're gonna know I also don't do
the math as fast as it's needed for that
but I have actually computed examples so
for example if you look at a session
think of during a session not a week but
one session of interaction just what's
the chance of seeing a certain behavior
and we say a session is five clicks and
each click involves only 40 resources
this is a dramatically smaller number
than reality most pages are a lot more
than what a resource is more session so
much longer than five clicks let's
assume that's its that's short of an
interaction mobile applications might be
in that space we're talking about that
sort of an interaction and only if you
already
that means a total of 200 things we get
and the interesting questions to ask
there for example how many of the people
that do this we'll see something worse
than the 95th percentile this is
something I've actually done the math on
okay so the number of people that will
see you sorry it will see better will
not see more so the number of people
that will not see anything worse than my
95th percentile when they're doing 200
different operations
that's 0.003 percent or more
specifically it means that 99.997% of
people doing this will see something
worse than the 95th percentile of the
individual operation but that's a good
example of showing that the 95th
percentile of an operation that you do a
lot of is usually an irrelevant thing if
you're trying to determine any kind of
reasonable part of your population only
a tiny sliver of the people involved
will ever state below that number and
all you know is that pretty much
everybody else 99.997% of people are
seeing worse than this but we don't know
how much was which is why you generally
need to keep more than the buddy 50%
Owens 98% though because people will see
that due to all the multiplication of
how many experiences times objects times
API calls you can simply think about if
if what you show me involves a hundred
things then you need two more nines in
you need to look at two more nines deep
into the thing then what you want me to
do if you want my 99 percent are to be
good
then the 99.99% of the thing I do a
hundred times needs to be good that's
kind of intuitive but another reverse
way of looking at that question is
suppose I wanted to know what 95th
percentile person would experience like
what 95 percent of people will see that
more better I probably need to look at
the 99.9 something percent of responses
as that's the number that 95 percent of
people will experience better because
you can because of those order of
magnitudes multiplication of how many
times it means a problem
is even much harder than we had hoped
yes the way this translates into sad
reality is when we look at things that
monitor servers components of systems
parts and services and microservices the
percentiles that we care about in those
should be a lot more nines than what we
care about with the people because
usually one human interaction involves
more than one database call so looking
at the 99% of a database only tells you
what everybody's gonna see Morstan it
doesn't tell you anything about what the
legs are get of them seeing for building
a distributed system where requests run
in serial through a bunch of components
and over networks I think what you were
just explaining about how response times
aggregating the browser also explains
how responses aggregate through multiple
steps in serial is that correct yes in
fact if we look at most things there's
some combination of parallel and serial
it's kind of like a tree so there's some
serial paths down the trail so even if
you need to do three things and you can
shoot all of them off at the same time
each of those will be things may be
serially waiting for some other things
to happen so for example you're being
asked to look up an item in a product
catalog the logic of the server that
does that sees your requests parses it
and then figures on that it needs to
perform a database of course so it goes
to a database and that's requested that
our basis figures out that this thing is
on this so it goes to a disk and ask for
our sector each one of those is an
example of a serial operation that will
not complete until another 0 operation
completes in modeling these you can
actually look at this as a sequence of
response times and service times that
are nested so the response time of
one thing is the service time of another
thing so if I'm the database and I ask
the disk for something then the response
type of this is my service time but the
question I ask that this may be alone
and it doesn't guessed it right away or
maybe there's a hundred deep queue of
requesting the disks that have been
there for other reasons so I'm waiting
in the line for a hundred other things
to complete before and whether this even
considers my request so the response
time from from the dish is longer in the
service time in that this is short but
what I see is the database is just the
response of the disk
similarly the thing that asks the
database as a similar you know whatever
the response time of the device is is
the service time of the things that
asked it all the way up to that
outermost response time whoever
initiated so at each level if you have
these composed services that are nested
then what is external response time
there's some wait time and service times
its component of that the service time
is comprised of response times that
eternally half wait times and response
times okay so you meant that you said
the wait time they're typically time
spent in queues what are some of the
different kinds of cues that exist in a
typical system so queues and wait time
are not necessarily the queue you would
think of as a data structure so the wait
time functionally is the time from when
you wanted the service to happen until
the service started to do its work
between the two you waited and
technically you're waiting in some queue
somewhere no it could be that your
request arrived at the thing that does
the work and it's got some resource to
the service you're waiting in a queue or
maybe it just arrived in a socket but
nobody's ready yet to the socket is a
queue or maybe it didn't even arrive
there it's still sitting in your socket
because back pressure has made it not
sent or maybe even you could even make
the send call on your software because
of the previous one is blocked and you
backed off
you could be anywhere in the chain
between wanting to do the thing at the
time you wanted to and the service
actually starting the water anywhere in
that chain is a is a weight and those
cues could be any spot anything that
where this will eventually happen that
is not yet started would be okay
so I'm aware for example that in a
spinning hard drive that has one head to
read the platter that all the requests
to read and write are ultimately
serialized
to that one head so with that big one
example if that would be a good example
but then if you look at the different
protocols you talk to disks with some
protocols were allow you to post
multiple requests and you know you can
post the next request before you get the
next one and then this is the cute
there's a queue inside the disk logic
that is holding every question and some
of them will say until I respond you
don't get any another one and then the
queue is gonna be on your side and the
reality is about any combination of it
to no source of late she tells that
you're very well informed about his
garbage collection how does garbage
collection introduce variability into
the latency of application so garbage
collection or more specifically garbage
collection pauses are an unfortunate
side effect of how some managed runtime
Spanish memory whereas they need to
perform the action of garbage collection
they will phrase the entire application
until some phases complete and when that
happens if that takes some perceivable
amount of time or if that is a dominant
reason for a stall or a pause then that
tends to be the thing that makes waiting
happen the thing an excu accumulate the
thing that makes the service that you
are waiting to start not yet started
so garbage collection pauses are a
dominant cost for that and garbage
collected systems but those pauses are
no different and behavior or
functionality than other reasons for
stalls of causes so the simplest one I
like to tell people to think about is
you can always know their server and it
halsy install your process that is a
pause until you let it go again the
garbage collection pause is no different
than that except that it doesn't when it
wants to
a awesome you're scheduling quantum and
a CPU where you've been running for a
while now it's somebody else's turn and
you'll get CPU again ten million seconds
later that's a 10 millisecond stall that
again is a little different and a pause
that happened in one of the controls New
York DC pause there are many other
causes like interrupts and our savings
moans and stalling Fitness can die ho
many things could cause you to stall
when you work in the field ER and you
look to improve these you tend to make
educated guesses about which dominant
ones are likely and try and reduce those
you know when you're running Java or
Python or JavaScript in it is very
likely if that garbage collection pauses
are one of the dominant factors in
hiccups stalls whatever we call those
things and those will invariably show up
as tail latency numbers that are very
high that are orders of magnitude higher
than the typical average so while your
average or typical might be seven
millisecond response you might
occasionally get a half-second response
so I'd like to think about this problem
of I'm trying to design a system a
retail system with a certain latency
characteristics and I could see a couple
of ways to come at it but let's say the
first way is I'm going to try to control
the latency of all the components get it
down in the range I want
I took queueing theory in school we had
these graphs where as you put more
throughput through a system that you see
latency increasing so what what are we
looking at when we see that graph what
is it is that a real description of
reality or does that leave something out
so I actually think there's ranges to
the response there if you take a system
and you saturated meaning you ask it to
do work at the rate it can do that
work or a little more then your cues are
always going to be fault there's always
a full line you're basically doing
things as fast as you can which
fundamentally means that the response
time measured from that side will be
your service line plus the deepest cue
you have italy long if you have room for
thousand things and the cubit will be a
thousand things and the cue is your
saturated so at that edge of the system
where you've saturated it response time
will always be terrible it's almost
irrelevant to measure how bad it is
because it's erratically in it I
couldn't do any worse I mean if I can do
a thousand things a second and I ask it
to do two thousand things a second what
actually happens is the line gets longer
by thousand things each second the
longer the run is the longer the
response time it's just the line keeps
getting longer and longer and even when
I finish the test it could be a million
more things to do so for the many add
saturation of post saturation response
time is actually an irrelevant behaviors
not a metric that matters now what
happens before saturation is interesting
and there's this obvious other end of
the spectrum of it I don't when there is
no work being done and you're just doing
one operation there's nothing in the Q's
you're basically measuring the service
time of the system because you're not
waiting anywhere and that's a nice happy
area and there's a special of how this
behavior how do things begin between
this idle point of the saturation point
that has a lot to do with questions of
arrival times and consistency of
execution if you had a perfect arrival
time let's say I can do a thousand
things a second and I'm only asking for
a hundred things a second but beyond
just saying this other things a second
will be a hundred that seems a second
spaced out ten milliseconds apart
I see so if you could do thousand things
per second and a thousand requests
arrive all at once it will still take
you time to assess it'll take me a
second to take the to get the last one
but if there's thousand things arrive
one every millisecond each one will make
the same rate you can see them got it so
so an interesting observation is when
people talk about
rates per second there's an inflation
assumption that we don't care about
response times below a second because if
we did we wouldn't be talking about a
thousand a second we'd be talking about
one per millisecond so suppose if what
you care about is I want to make sure
things start below ten millisecond
response time can you do that at the
thousand a second their answers I don't
know because you didn't tell me if I
arrived in the same millisecond or not
you might get the thousand wait a second
and then all thousand years on and they
took all of them took a second okay but
if what you told me is I need to get the
answers in ten milliseconds or less and
then my question would be so how many
messages will give me in ten
milliseconds as long as it's less than I
can perform in ten milliseconds I'm good
with that
so we need the rate per time unit should
we know the scale of response time we
care about so when we look at databases
what we want response them to be in
milliseconds or little tens of
milliseconds our actual mindset should
be how many message for 10 milliseconds
rather than how many per second
obviously people normally talking for
second messages but the distribution of
arrival time is important so that's one
part of the modeling that is hard if you
actually look at actual arrival time in
real systems it is nowhere near nicely
spread evenly so you can try for both
it's nothing you can say assume that
within a second instantaneous rate is 5x
per second rate it highly depends on the
domain in the U students but the
instantaneous arrival time in a fraction
of a second is more important than the
rate per second one of the interesting
observations of sceners in
mechanized systems like financial
services systems there tend to be a much
higher natural concentration of arrivals
than in things that are humans
interacting with systems so for example
in a trading system used me there's some
sort of information ticker going around
the wall like reuters that takes four
times a second and every time reuters
provides new information some algorithms
will decide to perform some trades very
quickly after which means that if you
look within a second
you see spikes at the rival four times a
second they're not evenly spread there's
just a lot here and then a lot there and
all out there and there's stuff in the
middle but this is very very high spike
of arrival brownie a lot more than five
eggs that typical that's because there's
some Universal clock everybody's
sticking to it synchronized in time and
everybody outside
luckily humans don't work that way we
don't have that accurate clock which
synchronizes all of our clicks to come
in at the same millisecond of a second
so when humans are interacting systems
you tend to have much better smear point
not the interesting artifacts that you
see if you study arrival times deep
inside some systems though is that
sometimes you'll see human interaction
that seems to arrive in spikes during
the second and the reason that happens
is that some system in the middle was
doing polling and batching work mmm it
didn't immediately react it said let's
gather all the stuff you're doing the
last 10 millisecond and then do it and
by doing it I created these spots and
it's not the batching that it is the
fact that the batching happens on the
spot so they start online and you get
these things that you would think a
random but actually your life and spikes
that's not a bad thing it's just an
interesting observation of distribution
there so arrival is one key thing right
you need to design for the peak arrival
time within the response time you care
rather than some average okay so it's
not enough so I'm going to build this
online store and I will I'm going to
engineer it for page loads within 500
milliseconds you still need to tell me
what the arrival rate is that will
sustain that learning timing so yeah if
you want 500 millisecond response times
and you need to know how much can arrive
in 500 milliseconds if I'm 150
milliseconds you need that the other end
of the same that's the arrival time
itself only hypothetical systems
consistently execute and respond at the
same time all the time things happen to
systems all the time whether it's
interrupts Quantic switches and
scheduling or page faults or garbage
collectors or power safe or you're
running on a cloud in a virtual machine
and your neighbor of a notice of time
there are things that even though the
averages will be good will disrupt
you're in the
ratios of making longer shorter every
time you have a disruption that even
momentarily makes you fall behind not
only the operation you did takes longer
but in queue builds up so if I didn't
get any CPU time to work on things for
the last 20 milliseconds and you are
sending a thousand things a second I
mean a perfectly even rate I have a 20
entry queue now to deal with and
actually drive down but things are still
arriving which means it will take me
time to drive them so the queues and the
spikes that arrive as a result of
momentarily slowing down as a draw that
effect an additional tail there's a lot
of thought gone into building reliable
systems out of unreliable pieces we know
that instances on the cloud fail and
come and go every type of device in our
network and hardware fails yet we can
build reliable systems that far exceed
the reliability of any individual
component now is there a similar
thinking process around latency where I
can't get rid of queues I can get rid of
work of building up at different places
in the system dealing with hard drives
that are gonna sometimes take an extra
500 milliseconds to do a read how can i
engineer an entire system with
predictable latency out of pieces that
have variable latency I don't like the
term predictable licensee because most
people that deal with it don't deliver
it so for example we do not deliver
bound latency in the practical
tournament commercial systems hard
real-time systems hard pacers I can
assess probably we do but in most of the
cases where looking to shape latency
behavior including the tails and high
percentiles to fit within limits so we
want the 99.9 percent oil to be below X
and all those even though the components
we have our worst than that now there
are multiple ways people can go about
delivering that you can go to so the
ultimate
more complex that's super practical to
build into our system out of but very
useful things like systems that perform
the same thing down redundant paths at
the same time and it's enough for one of
the paths to complete for you to
actually continue to work without even
waiting for the other graph stability
those kind of item potent designs where
you do something and you're gonna get
the result the same result even if you
do it three times are great but they're
also very hard to design well in the
large system so you might find
components that work like that or or
things like work that where it's enough
for one or two things to be alive and
respond and you take the first response
and run with it in for example systems
like zookeeper will work on a corn-based
protocol where enough arrival is enough
to move forward so even if you have
laggers whether they failed or just come
in late it doesn't matter but most
systems are not built that way most
systems get complex enough that it's
really hard to achieve the state
consistency promises needed to do this
so instead what you do is you work
around detected failures the simplest
way to do that is timeout and retry you
know you need something you I need to
respond in less than a second I'm not
going to wait a whole second I'll wait
50 milliseconds you to give me an answer
I'm going to ask it again and again and
again I suppose the thing that you ask
has a 99 percentile or 50 milliseconds
that means 1% of things are not going to
come back but those 1% in with retried
and 99% of those will come back some
right 4/9 is 100 milliseconds by six
nines 150 milliseconds and that part of
the operation is now in a six nines of
150 milliseconds which might satisfy
what I need for the end result and I can
put a bunch of these together and we get
those so the basic mechanism of a
timeout a short timeout and a retry
mechanisms where you work into the
system the fact that you might be tried
two three times before you get the
answer you
enough time to do that is a good way to
work around relatively unreliable
response time and retry that also tends
to work well for both situations where
the thing you're waiting for the answer
answered but not quickly enough or that
it actually failed and and you just
wouldn't got the answer name somebody
else if we push that concept to one more
level downstream could I say make a
request say here's what I need I need it
in 50 milliseconds or less and if you've
worked on it for 50 milliseconds you
don't have the answer just to give up
because I'm gonna go get it somewhere
else so this is where the circuit
breaker concept starts coming in the
problem that happens when you build
simple time on retry mechanisms is that
if you have actual failure that's
actually pretty good
so something filled you just okay it's
not affected but the effect you get from
time on Sandri choices that you're
generating more requests for the same
work that you needed and you can end up
taking a system that's now slow because
it's under load it's been slowed down
and it takes longer than the timeout to
produce a result it does produce the
result but by the time it gave the
result you gave up and asked again
producing more works lying it more down
and then it kind of goes downhill from
there and it's doubles the the way to
prevent these kind of cascaded system
effects and they happen at many levels
way beyond just one step is to try to
react to timeouts as a very bad thing
that makes you not even try for a while
so so it I think they're just kind of a
violent reaction to failure where what
you're actually saying is since I failed
I can try to push harder
but rather than push harder to induce
value I will Iza I'll fail quickly so
whenever you have the option so you know
I just don't have that as reduce and by
doing that you've saved the system that
was misbehaving from additional pressure
and in circuit breakers fundamentally
are things that attempt to react to
performance by B every bad reliability
by easing up the pressure rather than
pushing harder hoping that that ease up
will allow the system to you to catch up
or work the Institute's parameters it's
a form of flow control where you know
hey I'm not doing well don't you make me
do even more work this is a way of
limiting the operating range of the
system so that you get the lates you
want for those requests that you're able
to serve and not taking on more requests
in that yes but fundamentally doing that
requires pushing back and that push back
often means accepting that something
won't happen now there are many
applications in the world where that's
very acceptable there's some that are
not
but if you look at things like serving
ads or putting up recommendations or
even Auto completing your typing if
every once a while it didn't happen it's
not terrible you have to put in one more
letter before you got it or complete you
wouldn't know if the ad that you nobody
sold you anything well we could have
made some money but all we did is lose
an opportunity didn't may give you a bad
impression so for example I have this
room I get an ad if I can't figure out
what ad to put you I'll just put the big
image there that I don't have to think
about I don't have to figure out that
you've gone hiking recently and maybe
want to buy a tent I just show a stock
image right you don't really know the
difference and I just lost an
opportunity so there are many things
where you can actually go back to the
application the valued application tries
to provide and push back on that say is
it okay if we sometimes just don't do
this if we just we don't do the smart
thing we do a dumb thing instead because
we can't do the smart thing fast enough
as long as I did this one thing 99
percent of time any nine point nine
percent I'm probably okay and those kind
of things
basically react where circuit breakers
don't attempt to actually get the answer
they get a cheaper answer or worse
answer and move on from a business
standpoint then let's come back for this
example building the store you could say
I can't guarantee that I'm gonna show
you all 30 shirts with all the chrome in
less than 500 milliseconds but I'm going
to show you some shirts in less than 500
milliseconds the
that I could get back right from a
business standpoint is that sometimes
better say I'm gonna show you what I've
got in reasonable amount of time and
make you wait to see everything I think
there's a subjective specific question
sometimes this sometimes no so I think
there are a lot of cases when answer is
yes especially when what you are doing
now will never be repeated but there are
many places where the answer is no and I
think shopping is actually one of the
examples where the answer is no but
people browse to shop they usually don't
immediately choose and buy something
that they found and if you actually look
at the patterns that people go through
you'll go look around and come back
which means that they expect to get the
same answer the next time or they won't
know where to find the thing that they
want to go back to right it's Schloss
somebody shuffled all the clothes on it
which is why in that specific example
you don't actually want to repeat the
same answers you give the person before
so you can't just do a best-effort and
then later do a better one what they
need to see is the same thing like oh I
remember that I had the cool thing over
there I think I went here and here and
here to see it and if they go here and
here to see if they need to see it so
that's an example where if you expect
they're like what you see it you expect
to have some sort of been still being up
tomorrow or today or and I want to click
and you can't just do the best you can
for that part and do the best you can
again although I the extremes maybe it's
okay but there's certainly a lot of
places where that's not the case where
the experience you're going to be that
will never be seen again ads are a
perfect example nobody expects to see
the same ad again so after you have
complete freedom to do the best you can
and no more and if you do it again next
time and you don't get the same result
that's fine yeah I almost get annoyed
when I see the same ads over and over
and over again because I've already
decided I don't need that product and
it's probably a bad idea for them to
waste that space in front of you because
you haven't clicked on it right yes so
the same kind of thing so there are
certainly domains where best you can
change what it is every time just get it
out of the way is a great way to do it
in there are cases where
no it's just wrong it obviously when it
comes to things that correctness is
critical like the balance of your bank
account best effort calculation of the
balance of your banking and it's not a
good way to go when you can't calculate
you it's better to wait and give you the
algorithm to give you a lot yeah I
worked in retail location I was tall but
people understand the domain that people
are willing to wait quite a long time
after they have decided what to buy and
put in the payment information and hit
submit
and if you can take tens of seconds to
complete the charge transaction and
that's acceptable so that's I don't
think that's true anymore
it is true that they're willing to wait
a lot longer for that than for it to
other operations but a lot longer for
that today is probably below ten seconds
in fact I could say from personal
experience that I've run into the
situations where I've decided never to
shop somewhere again because of that
specific cases you know sitting in a
hotel room I'm booking a flight might go
for that cheap place you booked flights
whatever that is get everything ready
everything and then going into the
information fill it up and you know you
click and it says and you've got the
rotating thing and it says we're
processing your order do not go back do
not hit me try just wait
anyway but after twenty seconds you
start thinking what I do now and after a
minute you start thinking I need to
leave the hotel room and check out what
do I do now and at some point you get
annoyed close the laptop don't know if
you bought the plane ticket or didn't
don't know if you need to buy it again
whether you spend twice or not leave an
actual reaction to that is I'm not going
through these people okay so I think
that the like it's perfectly acceptable
for people today right now I think to
wait on the order of ten seconds for
checkout authorization payment kind of
stuff that's still an acceptable round I
think it's gonna keep cutting itself
down mobile behavior is a big reason
expectation at
although level now is much less like for
example Apple pay you don't expect to
put your thing there and sit there and
stand in front of the counter for 10
seconds other people are waiting yeah
expect roughly 2 to 3 seconds next but
that's that's the checkout on the way to
checking out you browse you put things
in the shopping basket you looked at the
shopping basket you change your mind 15
times you did all those things those
nobody's waiting 10 seconds a second
that's too long for mostly those things
I want to talk a bit more about the
garbage collection in relation to this
set of problems we had Monica Beckwith
on time about other garbage collection
if she talked about their different
durations of pauses and have some
control you may have some control over
when they run so one technique we
covered was if you know that a
particular JVM it needs to do a major
collection and compaction which will
take two seconds you can pull that one
out of the rotation experience this two
second pause while it's not serving or
question and put it back are there other
techniques where you can manage the
pause behavior well this is a place
where obviously we will have strong
opinions and we think it's a terrible
way we think it's a waste of engineering
time or more importantly it's a great
example of the length of people who go
to duct-tape engineering a problem
around the problem that you in the big
system and as ole we have a really
simple solution for this those pauses
should never happen and they go and when
you take the process of way you find
that people take away the need to even
ask the question of how do I predict
when a two second pause will happen so I
could take the thing out of rotation and
hopefully predict correctly and then
bring it back and deal with the
rejoining of a customer leaving the
question and all the other things that
it's a great example where disruptions
execution that happen for no good reason
except for a garbage collector angsty
paws are are they both brake application
behavior or but also force engineers to
come up with really complex ways around
the problem so people have absolutely
done what you described most people
don't most
or do not have the ability to
predictively take a node out of the
cluster because it is about to have a
problem but sometimes you're able to do
that prediction the thing that makes it
hard is it's really hard to tell when a
collector is going to pause if it's
going to pause the approach I've seen
some people do is to say well
empirically it takes at least an hour
between the pauses so every half-hour
I'll take it out and force it to garbage
collector to do a full GC and the full
pause and bring it back and hope the
last another at least half an hour
before that happens again and that tends
to work the tens is a strong point there
because garbage collection pauses do not
happen because time has elapsed average
box deposits happen because enough work
has been done to so you've caused
garbage collections happen at whatever
level it is fragmentation around a
patient and for example if your loads
just grew by 30% you're doing 30% more
work chances are that your garbage
collectors will happen for 30% more
frequently now you need to predict the
model that tells you based on the
current workload how long I think at
this rate I'll do at this rate at that
rate and now you're starting to look at
load versus predicted time and that's
not that simple because maybe it depends
on that kind of things you do and the
size of documents you process and the
color of the shirts you sell and who
knows what else and now you need to
strongly predict with this machine that
is imperfect will do in the future and
when the bad thing will happen so these
are not impossible tasks but they
require a lot of glue do engineering we
believe the approach of just these
problems should not be occurring garbage
collection pauses are they belong in the
1990s and shouldn't have made it into
this minute so us area I'd like to delve
into is trying to engineer a system for
bounded latency how should I be
monitoring what should we be looking at
and what should we be responding to so
I'd like to separate the design or
architecture from of how to
how to even make the system put the
parts together from how to achieve
certain latency bounds and behavior once
I've got a functional system and I think
the good news is that while the models
and the percentiles and others are
really hard to predict they're actually
fairly hard to measure well the art of
capacity planning is usually not one of
predicting what you will need but
empirically it arriving at the number so
if you think about it if you've defined
your requirements your requirements
would probably be you know we track
money correctly and one plus one is
actually two for that kind of math we
respond to most people in a snappy
manner that's a median and 19% out of
there no second or two for whatever you
do or twenty-year pick a number we have
no more than 19 you know the 99th
percentile is worse but it's no more
than this the four nines are no more
than this maybe you have a more space
requirement you come up with what your
business your site your Web Store needs
so your times these are the end-user
India's or in user experience they can
experience on this site this is what I
want to achieve and I have a system and
it's been built to do it and the typical
operation does fit in that if the
typical operation doesn't go back to the
drawing board figure out how to shorten
your operation so it's not a sizing
question at that point if if do it if it
idle you still can't meet it you just
your numbers are wrong but if you have a
system that could usually do it but the
question is okay so how many servers do
I need to do that what I like to tell
people is think of this is a term in
terms of managing misery you've defined
a requirement and the actual requirement
is to not fail or to only fail your
requirements a minimal number of times
per day you can say these are my
requirements okay if this fails a
hundred times a day and 100 million
operations but no one then the actual
question you're asking is how many
machines how much capacity do I need
such as that will be true the way to
establish that is to try
load it up
with one machine with two machines with
ten machines 20 grow it to the point
fine through through simple searching
how many machines are at that edge of
being right at the misery point and then
in reality capacity planning is about
tripling the number and going home so
you figure out where it collapses and
the actual answers I don't want to be
anywhere near that so give me a lot more
and let's be done with it
pasady planning is about the prevention
of crossing the mystery line and that's
that can be very effectively done with
empirical techniques rather than
theoretical modeling techniques so take
your system see how it behaves figure
out where the line should be press it to
that line and whatever artificial way
you want to do it by constraining the
system and that will establish what you
need now if you're fairly small you
would do that in a lab or you would
monitor your systems compare them to
where you are and probably be
conservative about numbers if you are a
very large operation you can actually
play games with saying I can't do this
well in the lab but I'm going to
experiment on 1% of my users so I'll
take one percent among users and and
constrain them to only a certain set of
machines and play games with how big
that needs to be before I make those 1%
miserable I'm not doing it to everyone
establish that a little bit and go and
the cool thing about being able to do
that if you're an Amazon er is that you
can often establish your requirements
not just
capacity by doing that so how do you
know what you want you're 99.9% of the
eat well you don't actually know because
we don't know what it does to revenue
but what we can do is say let's take 1%
of the people and heart they're 99.9
percent on seen what it does to revenue
so that we can establish a model that
says what we want to do for the rest
yeah I believe that's how some of those
1.6 billion dollars per year numbers in
the magazine arrived at and one of what
I'm saying about that is I am willing to
bet that that's not the average or it
might have been to every year and it
doesn't tell you much about the
relationship it's that the thing that
made people not buying is not that the
average went up by a number but a lot
more of them
bad experiences and that's enough large
statement rather than actors and now for
that it cost them money or it decided
not to transact most online buying is
partly a judgmental thing but most
online buying is discretionary spending
it's it's it's to spending on a whim
it's you can reverse your opinion and
anything that makes people reconsider
loses money if they've thought of buying
it in this audience oppening musket
anything that gives them a change to
change our mind if that thing is you
didn't complete the picture he didn't do
that duck took too long whatever it is
that's only you're never making money by
doing that one click buttons are the
ultimate example of the power of not
giving you the opportunity to change
your mind yeah you click yeah you can
take it back by going and accidentally
finding and canceling something but the
other side where you put it in a
shopping basket but nothing happened
until you actually chose to check out
just gave you a long time to think about
maybe I don't need this like to wrap
things up guilt do you have a blog
Twitter or any place where people could
go follow your account YouTube channels
there's a few places I occasionally blog
in a couple places there's a blog called
stuff Gill says on Walk spot in and then
also Lacey tip of the day which is
relevant to this subject you can find me
on Twitter at Jill 1080i le eme I often
post on the mechanical sympathy Google
group it's it's one of my favorite deep
technical places to talk you'll find a
lot of postings by me there and I'm
probably a lot more four-post there than
at blog entries and there's probably a
lot of recordings of me speaking online
both on YouTube and our FAQ if you
google for my name and latency you'll
probably find some rents to look at we
had Martin Thompson on the show about
mechanical sympathy and then Azul people
like to learn more about the c4 or other
jvm or products at Azul where can they
do that
so Azul calm I'm used to be you have
hopefully the right information and the
website our flagship product zing
which basically eliminates garbage
collection cause this completely is
something you can just go to the website
and trial yourself run your application
and measure let's see how it looks
guilty thank you so much for speaking to
software engineering radio thank you
before software engineering radio this
has been Robert bloomin
getting software to your users quickly
and reliably is the most important part
of being a software engineer snap C is
cloud-based continuous integration and
continuous deployment tool lets you set
up in minutes with your github account
and within a few clicks we'll have your
first pipeline running discover and fix
your bugs quickly before pushing the
production by setting up stages from
simple ones to complex that run
automatically when you push your changes
need more speed run tests in parallel
with expanded workers and get your
feedback fast deploy to Heroku AWS and
more we even integrate with slack to
give you updates on your builds go to
snap CI slash software radio and build
test and deploy free for 30 days
snap CI embodies the lessons that
thought Works has learned from 20 years
of software deployment the same lessons
that have been written about by Martin
Fowler and J's humble check it out at
snap CI slash software radio thanks for
listening to se Radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our web site at SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]